Speaker 1: Hey, everybody. Ross Perot died today at 89, and I think he has a political legacy that's worth reflecting on. I remember in 2016, during
that
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): presidential cycle, there were a bevy of media articles and narratives being propounded that theorized
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): that Ross Perot really was the precedent for Trump in terms of the issues that they emphasized, in terms of aspects of their political style, in terms of being a, you know, wealthy businessman who was intruding into electoral politics and trying to upend the system. Because
if you
Speaker 3: recall, at least early on in the 2016 cycle, it was speculated that Trump
Speaker 3: might run as a third-party candidate if he didn't get the Republican nomination, or that he was going to blow up the Republican firmament and mounting this hostile takeover of the party that was going to end Republican politics as we know it. Now, it turns out that was a little bit overblown, actually a lot overblown, in terms of his governance.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Trump really has given most of the Republican institutional apparatus exactly what they wanted, especially with regard to judgeships. Most of his domestic policy agenda is perfectly in keeping with the pre-existing Republican honchos like Paul Ryan and Mitch McConnell. Now, there have been some deviations here
and there on
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): foreign policy, in particular in North Korea.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): arguably Syria, and then perhaps trade, but
in the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): main, Trump
Speaker 1: really is consonant with
what the
Speaker 1: Republican Party stood for even prior to Trump's
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): ascendance, and that is in some sense Trump's discredit because he had an opportunity to really break through long-standing partisan binaries and hasn't really governed
With
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): that in mind, for a whole variety of reasons, that's a longer conversation. But the point is, in 2015-2016, Ross Perot was frequently cited as
a
Speaker 3: precursor
Speaker 1: to Trump in a way. So
I can
Speaker 1: remember thinking during that time period, okay, this is at least a plausible theory. Why haven't I seen Ross Perot anywhere
in the media
Speaker 1: commenting on Trump, giving his insights as to what Trump stands for? Now, Perot was old at the time in his mid to late 80s.
Speaker 1: But he was alive, he was cognizant, it seemed, he was doing occasional public events, and he was last interviewed, as far as I can tell, in 2016, and perhaps even later. So it wasn't as if he was totally receded from public life. And remember, Ross Perot first ran in 1992, but he ran again in 1996. And in 1996, Ross Perot founded the Reform Party.
And that
Speaker 1: was the ticket on which he ran in 1996. And then four years later, who else but Donald Trump sought the Reform Party nomination. That
was when Trump was
Speaker 1: running for president that year. And he ran against Pat Buchanan. They had lots of nasty backs and forths. But, you know, it never really went anywhere. But nonetheless, you would think that Trump running to be Perot's successor was...
Speaker 1: would have given Perot some insights into, maybe not Trump personally, I don't know if they knew each other on a personal level, but at least politically, and that you saw virtually nothing from Perot on Trump. It's actually the one prominent political figure that I would have liked to hear expound on Trump
and the
Speaker 1: meaning of Trump, so to say, who never
really gave any public
Speaker 1: comments as far as I know. If you've seen those comments, send them to me because I actually have not seen them and I've looked.
Speaker 1: Um, but Perot, you know, he, he gave his thoughts on politics even well into his later years. He endorsed Mitt Romney pretty strongly in 2008 and 2012. He endorsed George W. Bush in 2000, sort of on the eve of the election, which was actually a somewhat significant boost to Bush because as well.
Speaker 1: Anybody who's passingly familiar with Ross Perot ought to know,
he ran
Speaker 1: against Bush's father in 1992,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): and the H.W. Bush team blamed Perot for their loss. Now,
whether Perot
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): actually
Speaker 3: is responsible for Bush's loss is a matter of contention. I think there's actually a very oversimplified caricature of Perot that has him siphoning votes exclusively from Bush and therefore costing him the election. There's actually been a lot of scholarship
on this.
Speaker 3: in the subsequent years, which suggests that Perot actually had a very heterodox coalition electorally. And
Speaker 1: there were aspects of his coalition that seemed to actually more disadvantage Bill Clinton
in
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): 1992. So the argument has been made that if anybody was disadvantaged by Perot in 1992, it was actually Bill Clinton, not Bush. But then again...
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): It's hard to really say with complete certainty because there are all kinds of variables and you can never prove a counterfactual meaning. If Perot never ran, Bush would have won. That's what a lot of Republicans still think now. But needless to say, he's a major
Speaker 3: figure in political lore. And so for him not to weigh in at all on Trump in 2016 was a bit odd.
So I
Speaker 3: tried to speculate as to why that might be. And, you know, I had been familiar with Perot...
For
Speaker 3: years, obviously, but something that occurred to me today about why he never waited on Trump, whereas
he waited on other
Speaker 4: political figures.
Speaker 1: And remember, Trump, at least nominally, was in line with Perot's agenda, anti-NAFTA,
is more
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): skeptical of trade generally than your average business-oriented Republican, both obviously kind of swashbuckling billionaire types.
But
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Perot actually was very insistent on subscribing to traditional morality, let's say. And that's not to make a normative claim as to whether his traditional morality was good or bad, but
Speaker 1: that's part of his identity or was. So for example, at the businesses he ran,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): he imposed a moral code on his employees where they were prohibited
Speaker 1: from having...
Speaker 1: extramarital affairs he was very scornful of adultery he
said in
Speaker 1: 1992 that he would not appoint knowingly any adulterers to his administration and he would later call bill clinton unfit for office on account solely
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): of his adulterous affairs now obviously pro had other criticisms of clinton that's why he ran against
him
Speaker 1: twice but perot
said on
Speaker 1: larry king in 1998
Speaker 1: that the fact of Bill Clinton's
personal
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): deviancies alone disqualified him from being regarded as fit for office. So that
might be a
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): reason why Perot maybe wasn't willing to weigh in in Trump's favor, because, you know, Trump was a philanderer, he was married three times, blah, blah, blah. Everybody knows the
story.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Perot always required personal modesty, especially in dress for women and men. So maybe a beauty pageant proprietor like Trump is not somebody who is naturally in sync with a Perot type. So just in terms of personal mores, you could understand why Perot might not have
felt...
Speaker 1: motivated to say anything positive about Trump, although he didn't say anything negative either. He kind of just abstained. He might have been the only person in America of any political clout who abstained from weighing
in
Speaker 5: on the 2016 election.
But
Speaker 6: there are other aspects of Trump's legacy that are, of Perot's legacy that are interesting.
In terms of
Speaker 6: an electoral corollary,
Speaker 3: one really interesting factoid
Speaker 1: is to look at how Perot performed in Maine
Speaker 1: in 1992, and then how Trump performed in Maine 24 years later.
Maine was the one
Speaker 3: state where Perot actually defeated one of the two major candidates, Bush and Clinton,
in overall
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): popular vote.
Perot received a
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): greater share of the popular vote in Maine than George H.W. Bush.
Now, Clinton
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): ended up winning the state, and he won both of the congressional districts, so it didn't make a difference in terms of the electoral college.
But it
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): showed that there was an appetite,
Speaker 3: especially in that region, for whatever Perot was promoting, you know,
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): kind of,
for lack of a
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): better word, protectionism, not quite isolationism, but having an alternate perspective on foreign
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): affairs, anti-trade, etc. And
I don't use
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): those terms as a pejorative because I think they're legitimate perspectives. But...
And 24
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): years later, Trump competed in those very same pockets of Maine, especially in the north of Maine and in rural areas where Perot overperformed. And
sure
Speaker 3: enough, Trump won the second congressional district of Maine, which entitled
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): him to one electoral vote, given how Maine
allocates its
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): electoral votes by congressional district. Only one of two states to do so, the other being Nebraska.
And
Speaker 1: that was the first time in history that Maine split its electoral votes in that manner. So you can actually
Speaker 3: draw a through line, at least in terms of results,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): electorally between Perot and Trump. And that
Speaker 1: is actually pretty interesting and I think warrants further study. Yeah.
It also
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): should be emphasized, and I mean, you see this when you read the obituaries, but it really should be, I think, underscored, that Ross
Perot was the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): most successful
Speaker 1: independent candidate for president in the entire history of the United States. I mean, that's hugely significant. He
was not a third
Speaker 1: party candidate, technically, really, when he ran in 1992. He didn't have a party. He ran simply as an independent.
Speaker 1: And he won a greater share of the vote in 1992 than any non-Republican or Democratic candidate had since 1912. And
that was
Speaker 1: Theodore Roosevelt, who ran on the Bull Moose Party ticket. He was a former president, obviously, so he was ubiquitously known. So
for Ross
Speaker 1: Perot, he's kind of...
Speaker 1: eccentric billionaire to come out of nowhere and really make that strong of a showing
should
Speaker 3: have been a forerunner to the kind
Speaker 1: of fluidity that we see in American politics now. And some people recognized that at the time, but it kind of all got subsumed into...
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): traditional, you know, kind of partisan
Speaker 1: politics. Ross Perot got 18.9% in 1992. Obviously didn't win any electoral votes, but 18.9 per 2% of the vote was almost 2 million, sorry, 20 million votes. And the guy didn't have a party. He didn't have an apparatus behind him. He later founded a party in 96, but he actually did worse in 96 when he had a party by a lot.
So
Speaker 1: that was actually a very significant phenomenon that, you know, it got a lot of study, but it's kind of gotten lost to memory now. And I don't know
whether Trump will
Speaker 1: comment on Perot. I don't know if he has yet, but Bernie Sanders did, hilariously. Bernie Sanders tweeted earlier today a photo of an Excalibur sword.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): that Perot gave to Bernie as a gift sometime when Bernie was in Congress. I couldn't, looking at the photo, tell what year it was from. My guess would be in the 90s.
But that
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): just
Speaker 1: shows you the kind of cross-partisan appeal that Perot really did have. If
you look at
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): the New York Times obituary, here's how they characterized Perot's support base.
It came from
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): across the spectrum, the New York Times said, from Republicans to Democrats, conservatives and liberals, mostly from the middle class. So you had...
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Everybody all across the spectrum who liked Perot for a variety of reasons, ranging from his kind of folksy and quirky personal style, to his blunt talk, to his
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): amusing aphorisms, to the policy stuff.
And for a
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): successful presidential candidate, you need to have some kind of combination of those to resonate, and he did. But it kind of,
it's actually a
Speaker 6: reminder that you shouldn't be oversimplistic in terms of your takes.
Speaker 6: as to what effect
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): third-party candidates have. I
remember in 2016, a
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): lot of people were just blithely assuming that the presence of Gary
Johnson in
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): the race would draw more support from Trump than Hillary. And the results didn't really bear that out. I mean, the results were much more
Speaker 1: ambiguous. It's plausible that,
Speaker 1: if you really look into the data deeply,
Speaker 3: that Gary Johnson actually disadvantaged Hillary more. So people don't have necessarily a coherent or a fully formed outlook when they're
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): assessing which candidates to support. It's kind of sporadic. It's kind of based on randomness a lot of the times. It's almost based on kind of vague affinities rather than a kind of rational, dispassionate assessment of a policy agenda. So...
You
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): know, Gary Johnson may have hurt Hillary more than he did Trump, and similar arguments could be made with regard to Perot. I
mean, just
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): because he was seen as a conservative and he was a Republican later on in his life doesn't mean that he actually cost Bush
the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): presidency. Now, there were some aspects of Perot that obviously...
which
Speaker 1: prevented him from winning the presidency. And in June of 1992, he was in the polls, very close, within the margin of error in some, to the two main candidates,
Bush and
Speaker 1: Clinton. But
then all
Speaker 1: of a sudden, pretty much out of nowhere, Perot dropped out. He
later came
Speaker 1: back in October,
Speaker 6: but there was like a several month time span where Trump, where,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): where,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Perot basically forfeited the huge advantages that he had, and the momentum behind him kind of receded. And if you look at why he dropped out, it's kind of hilarious. I mean, he essentially got bamboozled by a former police officer
Speaker 8: named, what's the name here? Sorry. Do-do-do.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Named Scott Barnes.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): who was a police officer in Southern California and apparently claimed that he had some vague involvement with the intelligence services, maybe the CIA, maybe something else, who knows. And Perot said
that he would
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): occasionally speak on the phone with this person. And Barnes convinced Perot that Republicans, who exactly, we don't know. Perot
was always
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): kind of vague about this.
that
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Republicans had launched this really intense and defamatory dirty tricks campaign to sabotage Perrault's candidacy. And Perrault claimed
that the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Republicans had photos of one of his daughters that were compromising and were actually going to physically disrupt his daughter's wedding by showing up to the wedding and disrupting it.
So rather
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): than subject his family to that potential...
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): And he later said that
Republicans are known to go around disrupting
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): events like this, and he actually speculated that a horde of neo-Nazis were going to be dispatched by the Republicans
Speaker 1: to disrupt his daughter's wedding. So Perot is obviously prone to some paranoia, kind of like Trump, and had deliances with fringe characters, also kind of like Trump.
Speaker 1: and always thought that he was under siege. And I'm sure there were some people
who wanted to
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): take down Perot, but based on what we know about this incident that led him to drop out, it was a total fabrication. The former police officer, Barnes, said some years later that he made it up.
Speaker 3: It
was a lie. And he
Speaker 3: basically successfully swindled Ross Perot and possibly cost him the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): presidency.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Because if Perot had remained in the race all throughout that summer into the fall, he potentially could have carried on the momentum that he had built up and, if not won the presidency, come closer than he did, even though he did historically well. One aspect of
Perot's legacy that
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): doesn't get talked about as much is his foreign policy views. Perot
was the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): only major presidential candidate
in
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): 1992, to actually question the Gulf War, which was then regarded as a grand patriotic triumph.
And Perot
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): was prescient on that issue because he just kind of, on an instinctive level, seemed to recognize
the
Speaker 1: illogic of the entire enterprise. And here's what he said in June of 1992, when he was kind of at the peak of his popularity and was getting
a lot of
Speaker 1: traction to the point where
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): he was seen
as a
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): possible victor.
in
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): that fall's presidential election. He said this on the Today Show
when he was
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): taking phone calls and somebody asked him to comment on the Gulf War. He said, we need to take these things apart, put them under a microscope and say, wait a minute, what happened here? For 10 years, we created Saddam Hussein with your taxpayer money.
Our president
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): was sending delegations over to burp and diaper and pamper Saddam Hussein and tell him how nice he was. That's all public record.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Then our manhood was questioned, and off we go into the wild blue yonder with the lives of
Speaker 3: our servicemen at risk because of 10 years of stupid mistakes and billions of dollars of taxpayer money. That's 100% right.
And that's an
Speaker 3: indictment of the bipartisan foreign policy consensus at the time. Bush and Clinton that year were essentially united with...
Speaker 3: on the wisdom and virtue of the Gulf War. Now, Bush did attack Clinton here and there for not being sufficiently enthusiastic about the Gulf War, but Clinton supported it and was pretty clear about that. So if they were a part at all, it was just by very, very minor gradations, whereas Ross Perot was saying the whole thing was a joke and phony.
And
Speaker 3: obviously, that resonated in the public to a large degree.
So there
Speaker 3: you have
Speaker 9: it. Those are some thoughts on Ross Perot, RIP, and
I'll talk to you
Speaker 9: later.